<?xml version="1.0" encoding="ISO-8859-1"?>
<info>
<item id="89" label="Dorsal columns" zorder="3" name="Ventral columns" x="0" y="229" tabs="0"><description><![CDATA[<p>The <b>dorsal column or funiculus</b> is AKA the <b>posterior column or funiculus.</b> It is that portion of the white matter of the spinal cord that is located between the dorsal median sulcus/septum and the dorsal lateral sulcus, i.e. the point of entry of the dorsal roots. Present bilaterally, each side includes two sub-parts, the fasciculus gracilis (located medially, closest to the midline and at all levels of the spinal cord carries input from the lower body and extremity) and the fasciculus cuneatus (located laterally, closest to the dorsal root entry and present only above T6 and carries input from the upper body and extremity).  Contains ascending tracts that carry tactile (discriminative touch), vibratory and proprioceptive input.</p>]]></description></item>
<item id="88" label="Dorsal lateral sulci" zorder="2" name="Ventral lateral sulci" x="0" y="220" tabs="0"><description><![CDATA[<p>The<b> dorsal lateral sulcus </b>of the spinal cord is where the dorsal roots enter the spinal cord. It extends the length of the spinal cord.</p>]]></description></item>
<item id="87" label="Dorsal roots" zorder="1" name="Ventral roots" x="0" y="217" tabs="0"><description><![CDATA[<p>A<b> dorsal roo</b><b>t</b> is AKA a <b>posterior</b> or <b>sensory root</b> of the spinal cord. It contains the axons of sensory neurons whose cell bodies are located in the ipsilateral dorsal root ganglion (or sensory ganglon) on the respective spinal nerve. &nbsp;As the nerve fibers leave the gangion they beaks up into multiple divisions known as rootlets as they enter the spinal cord at the dorsal lateral sulcus.  These axons terminate with the spinal cord and brain stem.</p>]]></description></item>
<item id="90" label="Lateral columns" zorder="0" name="Lateral columns" x="0" y="140" tabs="0"><description><![CDATA[<p>The <b>lateral column or funiculus of the spinal cord</b> is that portion of the white matter that is located between the dorsal lateral sulcus (point of entry of the dorsal roots) and the ventral lateral sulcus (point of exit of the ventral roots).  Present bilaterally, it contains both ascending and descending tracts including the clinically important corticospinal tract and part of the spinothalamic tract.</p>]]></description></item>
</info>
